welcome to the monthly Q&A with chopper
eggie I'm always pleased to be here and
to answer questions we will take
questions first from the patrons and
then we will take questions that have
been tweeted and then we will take
questions from the online chat so let's
get right to it please so the first
question is from the patron Quran it's
that's how it's pronounced apparently in
Danish and the question is where does
our human animal instincts fit into the
four kinds of knowing and how does
knowledge of the four kinds of knowing
help us transform and transcend so the
human instinct the notion of instinct is
actually a very difficult notion to pin
down because it's it's it generally has
referred to sort of completely innate
abilities not and that's very plausible
for organisms that don't do any learning
projects fighters it's unclear if it
applies to mammals although there's
probably some instinct or reflexive
behavior so I'll take it to mean
something that's innate and largely
reflexive and that is not altered
significantly in learning so I have
expected behavior along that line I have
a looming reflex so if things suddenly
change the ratio in my visual field my
head will move I don't have to initiate
that I don't learn that it's unlearned
behavior it's sort of wired in by
evolution to be adaptive so I'll take
that that's what we mean by instinct the
term is used very vaguely and sloppily
in general and many things that are
called instinctive behavior really it's
not quite clear that it should be called
that anyway so I won't get into this
academic cul-de-sac let's just take it
that that's what it's meant by the term
instinct so they are by
that has been rendered largely innate
due to our evolutionary history so
notice that that doesn't mean you don't
have to practice it either you could
make a very good argument that walking
is instinctive for us but that doesn't
mean that kids don't have to spend quite
a bit of time for the practicing for
that innate ability to come online so we
have to be very careful all of that said
here's what I think I want to here's how
I think I would want to respond to that
question in so far as evolution has
shaped us in certain ways for perennial
patterns across many different
environments
I think this would fit clearly into what
I call participatory node let's talk
again about what participatory knowing
is remember the four kinds are
propositional procedural perspectival
and participatory participatory is the
deepest and it's the way you should
analyze it that sort of three-ton time
skills
there's the evolutionary scale in which
what we're talking about is how
evolutionary processes have Co shaped
the environment and the organism to fit
together this is called niche
construction so what that means is
because here's the environment here's
the organism the environment could
select the pressure on organisms but
organisms also interact in their
environment to change the environment
and you get a mutual reciprocal shaping
and then for us at a higher level we are
also fortunate creatures of history
because we exist culturally and culture
also is something that through the use
of tools and technology and simple
systems culture is something that shapes
the environment to me and me to the
environment so this room around me this
is all a tool and then of course
unshaped see the tools on me to that and
then it also practices there are certain
ways I chose to talk and express myself
etc and then on top of it so on top of
that so there's the biological shaping
at the evolutionary timescale the
cultural post shaping of the historical
scale and then at the cognitive scale
there's the ongoing Co shaping of the
in terms of the sensorimotor alert I'm
sensing that's the environment impacting
on me but I'm also moving and adjusting
that's me changing the environment this
sensorimotor loop
so participatory learning is these three
layers in which the organism and the
environment at a biological cultural and
cognitive level are mutually shaping
each other that being said I think the
instinctive knowledge that you asked me
about and the way I try to rein it in
and specify that it met it's clearly
would belong to the biological
evolutionary biological level the
evolutionary timescale in which the the
organism and the environment have Co
shaped each other so for example the one
I gave walking is instinctive to human
beings bipedal ISM predates our species
by several species and it's an innate
characteristic and what happens is
because we're bipedal we have also
that's the way the environment selected
but selective pressure on us but our
bipedalism also enables us to do all
kinds of things that shape the
environment so that we make the
environment more walkable to us and that
that brings something out what is all
this participatory knowing generated
doesn't generate theories like
propositional knowledge it doesn't
generate skills like procedural
knowledge it does it generate
perspectives like respect eyeball
knowing what does it generate it
generates affordances it generates that
most of what's around me is walkable
being walkable right is not a property
of the thing or me it's a real relation
between us so disparate already knowing
that those three interim penetrating
levels of the mutual shaping that mutual
shaping creates affordances between the
organism and the environment and then of
course perspectival knowing prioritizes
making make some of those more salient
brings that into my conscious state and
then that gives me my situational
awareness and then that allows me to
apply and acquire skills and that gives
me my procedural no no way and then the
procedural knowing allows me to know how
to propose how the question other
definitely seek and how to state and how
to use language and that eventually
generates my proposition on the right
how it how does that all relate to
transformation and transcendence I think
we should understand transcendence in
terms of a deep transformation in the
dynamic coupling between an organism and
its environment and the deepest kind of
transformations are ones that and this
is this is ultimately a platonic notion
right that in a line stack those four
kinds of knowing so they are mutually
afforded in each of the constraining in
such a way that I am participating in
the generation of affordances and then I
am selecting the best optimal grip
within my perspective I will knowing so
that I get the best set of skills best
theories and what this affords is
ultimately hopefully a process that is
developmentally reliable in a
progression towards the overcoming of
self-deception systematically through
all the kinds of knowing and the
affordance of an enhanced coupling to
the world which would be an enhancement
in both a sense of our
interconnectedness our optimal inner
alignment and our outer connectedness
that to me would be the experience that
would be properly called a kind of
transcendence when we are going through
that systematic and comprehensive and
developmental change so as the child is
to the adult the adult is of this age
its development transcendence is
ultimately if it's going to be
transcendence in the aspiration to
wisdom it's going to be that kind of
overall comprehensive developmental
shift and so the animal instincts have
to be included in that I mean this is
one of my favorite quotes from Ichi you
know that the order can be flipped
it's German I wish Johanna says here the
he knows German much better than I do if
the quote is basically along the idea
that the heights of my spirituality we
reach into the depths of my sexuality
again with the sexuality is referring to
for my whole biological to Darwinian
heritage the spirituality is all those
ways in which I can transform and engage
in self transcendence so I can properly
situated within the stack of the four
kinds of knowing and in a developmental
trajectory in the dynamic couple into
the world the animal instincts would
play an important role the my concern in
answering this question has been
throughout their hit there's a form of
there's a version I always think of a
decadent version of Romanticism that
tries to locate sort of authenticity or
genuineness or an infallible way of an
infallible source of guidance for how we
act in terms of our instinctive behavior
and I think our instincts are just as
liable to drive us into self-destruction
and self-destructive behavior as
anything else but they should not be
demon arts they are not the Beast Within
they are adaptive they are needed and so
they have to be properly situated within
an overall just culture of our psyche so
the next question is from the patron
Tostitos which I just got to meet and
then one-on-one conversation recently
which I really enjoyed so I thank you
for that so this is really good question
do all cognitive biases stem from an
adaptive essence then its are they
particularly modes of our otherwise
adaptive heuristics
well you some biases are sometimes just
an artifact of how our cognitive
machinery slapped together by evolution
such a difference exists would have also
influenced their impact on
self-deception this is a really
insightful question and
so it's what I need to give more thought
to but I don't want to just pop out here
so I want it I wanted under said that
I'm gonna I'm gonna always try my best
but this is really much just you know
our on the fly I think it's probably the
case so I am convinced of the idea that
the brain is a kludge this is the idea
that you know it's a bunch of machines
that have been sort of slapped together
by evolution as Tostitos says but I also
but i also counterbalance that with a
lot of the more recent work by Michael
Anderson and the circuitry used an
exaptation hypothesis which is it
doesn't look like the brain as edgy as
we thought because a lot of stuff that
originally evolved for doing one
particular job has been exacted to doing
other other things so you know like my
standard ones my tongue has been exactly
for speech the Broca's area for
sophisticated control of their my right
hand has been exacted for managing the
syntax of my language and there's a
whole host of these and so because the
the increasing evidence for excitation
the brain isn't quite as crutchy
as it as we sort of thought it was
however I think it's also the case that
we fall prey to forms of self-deception
and self-destruction that are simply
anachronistic and the way the trustee
doe says so I think it's likely that we
have a problem with ice cream and that
people tend to over indulge in things
like ice cream because we evolved on a
savanna where you know and we're mammals
so milk yeah right and then lots of fat
lots of sugar thrown some salt make it
cold
oh my gosh we've you're on the savanna
so if you're going to come across
anything that has any of those
properties and and because of their
rarity and because of the precariousness
of your life you're going to gorge on
them when you see them and that that
machinery is still largely in place
because it only was significantly
challenged probably around
10,000 maybe 20,000 years ago that's not
long enough revolution to do enough so
we have this machinery in us that says
gorge on the ice-cream and we go into
the store the supermarket and because of
runaway capitalism we have 17,000
options of ice-cream and you can put in
you can buy them in various overwhelming
quantities and eat too much ice cream
we just need too much ice cream and that
self-deceptive self-destructive behavior
so I think that I would still want to
say that the majority and you see the
problem with the plum with saying even
that that's that that's maladaptive it
is it's only maladaptive if we have this
you know complex civilization wrapped
around this civilization collapses god
forbid then that machinery would again
become adaptive why this matters by the
way that the subtlety of this I'm sorry
sometimes you know we want really like
or it's not that easy there is a
hypothesis that's gaining plausibility
that the disorder we call it a disorder
and I mean no moral criticism by this
you know the ADHD hyperactive attention
deficit hyperactive disorder right and
it looks like that that form of
cognition is actually deeply adaptive at
- it's it's really good in a context of
being a hunter-gatherer and for 99.9% of
our history we were hunter-gatherers so
that behavior wouldn't have been a
disorder it would have been deeply
adaptive and probably can be
considerable social social social status
on these individuals and therefore
reproductive success which is why this
form of behavior is so prevalent
it's just now we wait you take these
individuals we take them out of
hunter-gatherer societies and we stick
them in this sedentary suffocating
purely you know superficially symbolic
world and they don't fit in without
difficulty now is that
piece of it being maladaptive is that a
case of them suffering from
self-deception it's very great so what
I'm suggesting in this as I'm trying to
unfold this in a nuanced fashion there's
probably a continuum of how we should
address the question of how adaptive the
machinery of self-deception is I think
it was always to some degree adaptive
because if it wasn't at least for a
significant part of our evolutionary
heritage adopted it wouldn't have the
motivational compulsion that it does so
maybe thing like that but then you know
other things
is it even maladaptive don't know so the
question is I think that there are
clearly patterns of self-deception and
self-destructive behavior that are not
running off sort of standard cognitive
biases and heuristics I still think they
are running off of adaptive machinery
but how adaptive that machinery is is
not a yes/no kind of quantifiable answer
because it's relative to our particular
historical and environmental context so
I think that does make a difference to
how we try and deal with patterns of
self-deception so there it means and
this is this is converted with something
I have argued that we have to think
different kinds and this goes back to my
answer to the first question and to
think of different kinds of intervention
strategies that are working at all of
the levels of the stack of the four
kinds of knowing they can reach down
into the animal instinct level and up to
our most highest personal cultural level
of cognition which means and this is
something that I have been putting quite
a bit of thought it because I've been
trying to think about the design
principles for an ecology of practice
and we need to have practices that have
complementary complementary
relationships with each other but we
also need to have practices that afford
this
of the four kinds of knowing and
layering of practices so that they can
be properly exact 'add in our
developmental progression so all of this
ties together I wish I could give you a
sort of succinct clear answer because
it's a really good question but I think
the answer is that we have to posit a
continuum and then we have to put that
into the dimensions of our design space
for how we try to think about creating
an ecology of practices so thank you for
that most excellent question I'm sorry
for the rest of you usually oh as he's
going on so long but I think it's a
really important question questions like
this that go to the heart of
self-deception and the heart of
strategies for intervening I think
they're ones that we shouldn't we should
turn to and keep trying to get better
and better answers on so Rob gray hi Rob
I have every month I look forward to the
meetings I have with Rob they're there
they're wonderful the discussions and
the sense of connection and it's just
great to have this ongoing relationship
with robinus Rob I believe is coming
also to the Sangha pretty regularly it's
just great - Rob asks a really good
question you have any personal observed
dead end practices in other words
practices you thought would be fruitful
but waste of your or the practitioners
time are there any practices you used to
do or wish you could do but our two time
resource intensive to do given the rest
of your goals this is an excellent
question the answer is yes it was a
practice that I took up that I had such
high expectations for and I pursued it
very diligently and I proceeded at a
couple times in my life the sometimes
practices take at different stages in in
your development and so you should come
back to them at some point I've done
this and this was the practice I read a
book and I recommend a book because I
think this were true for people I think
I came from the first investment Wagoner
and it's about lucid dreaming and and I
saw and I know also about Eastern
traditions that are similar green yoga
within Buddhist and
tantric lineages and so I had done some
earlier lucid dreaming work in my
twenties and when I was going through
Union therapy and I still do sort of
deep dream work and so that is conducive
to lucid dreaming and what he proposed
and you know I bought a bunch of books
on this or various programs to induce
more lucid dreaming and it's you know
it's quite a lot of effort you have to
do these reality checks throughout the
day as well do these trainings like I
was doing it I was being extremely
diligent my sadistic ego super-ego might
as well softly also may be sadistic evil
or my sadistic super-ego you know it one
fit one of the benefits from it is it
tends to make me willing to be very
diligent in the project yourself self
transformation so I pursued it quite
diligently and I not and you know and
all the books say it takes a long time
yep and and and that's true for a lot of
wisdom practices so I hung in and I hung
in and this is no criticism of this I
know that other people this works for
them I got one or two lucid dreams the
other thing is I'm a long-term meditator
that's also deeply predictive of lucid
dreaming and you know I talked to people
about it like my friend and colleague
Anderson Todd and and I had one lucid
dream and I had that powerful experience
that Wagner talks about I was able to
sort of within the lucid dream talk to
the Dreamweaver and it was oh wow and
then you get a sense of you know coming
into contact with sort of the numinous
depths of the psyche and then and then
that was it and it just sort of and I
was and the cost to benefit ratio was
just getting diminishing returns I was
putting more and more time and it was
like no that's it that's all you get and
I and I I'm not sure why that's the case
so I obviously I haven't developed the
expertise in the practice to get a good
sense of why it's not working and and
it's not because I can't remember my
dreams I can all that dream work needs I
can remember like names
it's it's it it's been disappointing
it's just been disappointing because I
thought that I saw this as a very
plausible way of trying to bring into a
naturalistic context some of the more
theoretic practices from neoplatonism
and also make another connection between
my current practice and uni of practices
and it just didn't gel for me so I've
reflected on quite a bit why is it that
sometimes these things Yelp and why is
it sometimes they go and it might be
that there's a whole host of reasons and
none of these are definitive in my mind
it might be that oh I mean sorry this
sounds oh sorry so try to take this the
right way but it might be by a lot
mycology of practices the the it's a
complex dynamical system maybe it's
working well enough that there really
wasn't much of a place for this or it's
not getting much of a functional purpose
purchase or it could be that I have some
resistance to it that because of my
videos in chronic background perhaps my
my particular you know religious
heritage is somehow interfering on a
level I'm not aware of perhaps it's my
age I'm getting older and so the
capacity for that kind of vivid imagery
is stunning to say to me which is also
makes things like active imagination
more of a challenge for me so I don't
know but the thing to think about that
is again first of all what I said before
if a practice doesn't work but you had
some sort of intuitive sense try it
again at another at significantly other
time another point in your life because
it might be just your the idiosyncratic
place in your psychobiological
development but it also might be that
certain things won't work for you
because of sort of more permanent
conditions within you or also because
like I say the relative success of
functionality of other things that are
happening for you so it should have
worked
all the predictors I did all the
research all the particulars there I did
all and it just didn't gel for me and so
I hope it's helpful for people to hear
that because what was helpful for me he
was wrestling with the fact I of course
I was disappointed because I saw it as
potentially powerful II but also to step
back and realize well there might be
good reasons also why it's not taking
for me or there might be reasons that
have to do with my mortality that I need
to deeply accept and so I think that was
a very helpful question Robin I hope I
was able to answer it about once I would
wish I could do more I would love to
take up sacred geometry which was a
practice of sort of doing a meditation
as you're sort of doing geometric proofs
sort of Allah you cleared it was part of
the Neoplatonic heritage because I have
a strong suspicion that sacred geometry
really bridges powerfully and extends
rationality through that bridging
between propositional and prospective of
knowing because of the way geometry
brings in perspective and shape and
construction procedural element but it's
also deeply rational and inferential
and analytic but I just don't have the
time to undertake it right now so that
was another great question deserving of
a long answer and I hope you found that
helpful Rob next question is from
another patron I believe is Janet
Stewart if you want to leave what are
might be the psychological effects on
women from the masculine use of pronouns
in all great with written works and
continued use in our spoken language for
most part I greatly appreciate
appreciate your sensitivity to this
issues and your lectures thank you for
saying that
matter to me and I'll finish the
question then start dressing it most men
in my experience and even women are
seemingly oblivious to how it offends
divides that excludes it troubles me
greatly so it's always been something
that I did you know there are works of
art too that come to mind what was a
fairly recent science fiction book
ancillary justice and the other way is a
classic science fiction for Clara Slough
in the left hand of darkness about how
in Blissett
we form models when we're reading given
the way language is used of course
because that's how all the models are
being generated in terms of language I
had an impact on me and part of it is I
think my upbringing I was my father was
quite absent I don't mean he didn't live
with us but he was all like not present
for a lot and so I was very much brought
up in a household of women my mother and
three sisters and so they taught me very
deeply that I should treat them even
saying this feels wrong but I should
look I shouldn't have to say it or even
it sounds even pretentious to be saying
it but they taught me that you know that
I should treat them as whole persons and
I don't need to say that they sacked me
down and oh no it just it was like it
was like an atmosphere around me that I
just internalized a very significant I'm
not claiming anything ridiculous and I'm
completely free from sexism I'm claiming
that and I'm not infected claiming you
know that I've worked hard on any
particular virtue I was lucky and then I
was brought up in a certain way it
helped me to realize things and then I
noticed that and I'm also as I have
undertaken this project of taking on a
public persona
it has concerned me now how accurate
this is or not but it's least pervasive
perception you know a lot of the IDW or
whatever we want to call it whatever
this is I don't I don't think that
pointing to Wikipedia I'm not part of
the intellectual dark web and part of
the intellectual deep web whatever that
means but I've noticed a preponderance
of the audience and the authors and I'm
on you know are male and I have always
wanted to try and make my work more
inclusive of women not just because of
my upbringing but also something that
I've noticed in my classrooms so it's
important to set up the culture of your
classroom very well and so for many
years now I make an explicit statement
asking women to participate more in the
class and I don't have any hard class
scientific evidence about that but I
have reliable and internal evidence that
when I do that more women participate
and then what I inevitably find is that
class goes better for everybody and so
it came to my mind that that would also
be the case for but if you'll allow me
the analogy and I don't mean anything
pretentious fire but that would make
this classroom go better and so I've
wanted as much as fossil fuel be
inclusive in that way I want to be as
inclusive as it's possible in all ways
but I'm addressing a specific thing
right now and like I say I'm
particularly sensitive to it because of
my upbringing and then like I said the
influence of some pretty powerful works
of science fiction that really called
this out for me I've also had the
reverse experience when when I was a
teenager I read stranger in a strange
land by Robert Heinlein and it may put
an impact on me in the notion of rocking
things sort of my first introduction to
you know what ultimately turns out to be
a Neoplatonic idea of new synthesis so I
decided as an out okay I go back
we I couldn't I couldn't read that book
I was I was about you know 30 or 40
pages in and is it's so incredibly
sexist and there's a figure in there
it's just ah
and so I like I said I've had both
positive it I have very powerful
positive and negative experiences around
its any particular in science fiction
and perhaps that's because science
fiction is the genre I know what to put
down on but oh who reads that right
except look around look around you know
why because science fiction is a genre
that in which the main character is not
any person the main character is the
world so science fiction is the form of
fiction that is most playful
of our worldviews and I think that's
actually deeply relevant to the pursuit
of wisdom and the transformation of our
fundamental understanding of ourselves
and reality and so I don't think it's
any coincidence that both my most
positive and negative interactions with
the phenomena ask me about head comic
science fiction so that's sort of the is
my own autobiographical explanation and
my pedagogical motivation for why I try
to be so sensitive about this and well I
think we should all make an effort to
address this it concerns me for example
and then what I can't do anything about
it and it concerns me that you know most
of the people that I talked about in
awakening from a meeting crisis
historically were men but if you notice
but if you notice when I get to the
cutting edge stuff the figures that are
most influential in my thinking right
now like la Paul and Agnes Callen and
Iris Murdoch are all women and that's no
coincidence either because just like the
classroom if we bring in the women
everybody benefits everybody benefits I
wish we could get past this I think
largely useless you know polarization on
this sorry but
I feel strongly about this again because
of the way I was brought up and the
impact of particular works of literature
on me and like I said from my own
pedagogical practice so I hope that
answers your question
another question from Ben Gao Ben is a
patron any really important person in
all this community the work he's doing
and so thank you Ben thank you
genuinely thank you a Ben's question do
you see the wisdom practices you teach
as relevant to existential risk humanity
faces I want to come back to the use of
that adjective in a second it's helpful
to individual well-being which is
already life-changing thank you for
saying that but these practices seem not
scalable enough to impact our policies
or culture this is one of Paul Van der
clays Critias well taken criticisms of
my work or can wisdom be hacked into
human beings in you've all her arias
conception of human hacking so first off
this is a minor note on Ben's question
existential risk I wish we could find
another term for threats threats to
human existence because the term
existential of course there's a
philosophical meaning which can be
confounded it confused with this sense
are something that is threatening human
existence so I give it a all of you out
there who are who are connoisseurs of
language I make it request for you if
you could come up with another way of
referring to risks to human existence as
a whole other than the adjective
existential so that we could keep the
philosophical sense of existential sort
of separate from what we're talking
about that in no way addresses Ben's
question it's just a request that I
wanted to make um I do think that there
there is a connection and I have been
working hard to try and bridge between
because I take this criticism and
related criticisms from
Jonathan pleasure seriously bridge
between the individual wisdom practices
and trying to get collective wisdom
practices going
that means wisdom practices within
distributed cognition so in a way that
is strongly and structurally analogous
to how I've argued how we can take
individual intelligence and recursively
boots drop it into rationality and into
wisdom I'm trying with the help of many
people to work out how can we take the
collective intelligence families and
distributed cognition and bootstrap that
up into collective wisdom that would
then act as a bridging point down to
individual ecology of practices and then
up to the networking this for the small
world network information of communities
and so I'm also getting on trying to get
deeply involved with community building
and then this takes me to something that
I've been talking about which is well
two things bridging all over this
verbiage right with art and and so I
hear the dawn recently and this was on
also screwed together in stone has taken
some of my work and I'll talk about what
it is in a second and then put it into
meaning way putting it to use it and so
disseminating these ideas artistically
through popular culture I think is very
important but it has to be growing I
mean it has to be handled like in a way
so keep it love me if we you'll allow me
to speak a little provocatively how do
we propagate ideas without getting into
propaganda and my hope is that the the
artistic expertise
dissemination of the ideas will keep
close pace and be constrained by the
degree to which communities are forming
and networking into higher art of
you know not a hierarchy like I said
annex what I want an extended small
world network of such community because
what I want to do and this is what Acura
the dawn put to music is I want to steal
the culture and what do I mean by that
what I mean by that is I'm not try I my
position is ultimately in this goes into
issues of policy my position is
ultimately not political it's meta
political I think exact time for
pointing that out to me because I don't
want something like the French
Revolution or you know the Russian
Revolution or the Chinese Revolution or
the Iranian Revolution these revolution
revolutions have not generally turned
out to be a good thing
political revolutions but I want
something like with the axial revolution
well what we got were in the combination
of the Renaissance the Reformation and
the Scientific Revolution but my primary
model that sort of splits the difference
between them is what you saw in
Christianity Christianity didn't try and
there wasn't a political revolution to
try and like topple the government or
anything like that and not because there
hadn't been Slade revelations in Rome
that person had been Spartacus comes to
mind but instead what happened was they
they built a new way of being and seeing
a new ecology of practices and that was
commensurate with community building and
it was commensurate with artistic
dissemination and symbolic expression
and what happened is this networked out
and in a bottom-up fashion the culture
shifted until the state which have been
even trying to oppress and suppress
Christianity had to had to accommodate
itself to the way the culture had been
stolen and we sell to all with the
elites took over yes they did but even
when the elites have taken over the
culture had shifted and the and things
that have been acceptable previously in
the Roman
structure were no longer acceptable
Christianity made infanticide an
immortal thing look around you we don't
practice infanticide we think it's a
horribly immoral thing before and this
is an argument made by Tom Horner but
before right that that Christian will
deport the christian stole the culture
infanticide was an accepted practice
both within Greek and Roman culture or
the fact that we should have welfare you
know concern for treatment of the sick
treatment of widows treatment of the
poor this is again although to some
degree it's been under threat by
neoconservatism this has been a
pervasive part of our culture all the
way through the Middle Ages doesn't mean
that those societies were perfect or
they didn't abuse people they do but the
culture had fundamentally shifted and so
I think I think we're at a point in
which we are we we are facing this is
the this is the point of Ed's question
we are facing comprehensive you know
threats to our existence and our
civilization is under strain
terrifically and so we I think are in
something in that ways analogous to the
end of the Bronze Age or the you know
the year three you know 395 in the
Western Roman Empire and if we it's not
like I'm doing it that's ridiculous
thing I'm just trying to help there are
so many I was on the conference
yesterday put together by Rafe Kelly all
these communities of practice that are
emerging to deeply try to stack the four
kinds of knowing critic colleges and
practices that reliably and
systematically help people respond to
the meeting but it's growing it's
growing it's growing is it going to win
out I don't I don't know but even if you
know maybe the project is to try and do
what Christianity did you know the Roman
at least in the West
Christianity saves the eastern Roman
Empire as far as I can tell but my son
Jason would know that better than I do
but you know it doesn't say the Western
Roman Empire this in fact was one of the
you know the pagan critiques of
Christianity didn't say the restaurant
row of an empire but what it did is it
gathered the candles of wisdom and
knowledge and the new forms of
sociability and the new forms of knowing
and the new ecologies of practices and
it preserved them and it soda seeds and
it kept a socio economic social cultural
structure going so that a new
civilization did not have to start from
scratch the way it did after the
collapse of the Bronze Age so maybe
that's the project were engaged in and
then we have to be able to connect to
things that will exceed our own lifespan
try to sow seeds now that will make a
long-term difference maybe that's a
grandiose vision but maybe this is a
time for larger visions because and
again even saying that sort of bothers
me because you know we do need larger
visions but we don't want to give it to
utopic thinking the problem with utopia
is this is a control level bias when we
look into the future we tend to conceive
of things that are very high abstract
level of construal and so we don't
notice all that my new should details
and all the side effects you know you
know that this happens you it would be
great if I learned Japanese and I can
see all the wonderful things and I
picture that and then I start taking
Japanese and all it means getting up at
this time and travelling here and
writing there and you know being
embarrassed when I make a mistake oh
there's all this detail and that's the
problem with utopia if they're very very
very bound up with construal level
policies like that extra level bias so I
hope other people and I'm trying myself
to be as reflective as I can that we can
talk about these larger visions without
falling prey to that kind of utopia
control level VARs so then you asked a
big question and you asked about a big
picture and that's my answer to it and
then that's my sort of at the end of
Tellman is myself corrective caveat to
my answer
I hope you found that helpful uh here's
a question from Luke G who's a patron
well I'm currently dealing with my
father's death expecting a second child
to be born within days while studying
MBA four-year MBA and running a family
business that is struggling theater
Kovach at the same time my super ego
sets a huge expectation on my
performance I understand that
it feels very oppressive if these are
not met what would you advise how to
stop seeking for certainty and become
adaptable what would be relevant here so
I I appreciate first of all your
question and sort of the way things are
there in your question one thing to do
would be to try to separate out these
various things in your mind because we
do have a tendency for what's called
encoding specificity all of these things
are stressful but most of them are
negative and therefore we tend to
package them together as one thing but
if you could sort of pull them apart
because you need to respond to them in
different ways so there is nothing
anyone can say to you about grief other
than we have if we have gone through it
and I have lost both parents is to say
that we understand what we're it's how
the words are useless but they're
there's nothing that humanizes a human
being more
then going through grief you can't you
can't solve grief you you have to grow
into another person in another world so
that the size of the hole that grief
makes it you shrinks by comparison you
don't really get rid of that hole what
you do is you grow a self and the world
that is more encompassing such that that
hole is comparatively not as large in
you but it if the idea is I will stop
missing my father that's not going to
happen and you wouldn't want to be
ultimately the kind of person that was
incapable of grief the kind of person
that would stop remembering your father
what does happen and there's no quick
way through this any of the attempts to
short-circuit grief are damaging or
damaging what can happen though as I say
is if in community with others grow into
a different more expansive person in a
deeper world is in that hole only in
comparison shrinks then the degree to
which you relive your relationship to
your father diminishes so it doesn't
have to be as biting to you it will
always I predict we're always come with
a sense of loss but right now that sense
of loss is tending to mas you know a
more a fuller picture of your father the
loss the loss of super salient to you
right now and so the salience of the
loss through this comparative shrinking
of the hole in your world because that's
what a death is every person is a
doorway to a way of being in the way of
being in the universe and the way of
being inside of us
right your father is a doorway into the
depths of your psyche and it was away
and your your father you know as a way
of for you seeing into the depths of the
world and that is taken away it's a cap
so the loss is super salient to you
right now but if you go through this
long process what could happen is the
loss isn't so super salient and that
that whole it is such a feeling of
privation right now does it it becomes
less comprehensive in your experience of
the world and of yourself and other
other aspects in which your dad is woven
into that come to the fore for you and
then you start to experience again this
won't happen this will not happen soon
but you start to experience gratitude
and also forgiveness for the ways you
that might have hurt you
and so that's about the grief about your
expecting your child there's that's
where you can really trust you have to
trust your biological heritage you have
to trust the love you share with your
partner you have to trust that yeah
there so there's an instinctive and
relational machinery that will provide
to bear be willing to learn be willing
to share be willing to make mistakes and
remember that as long as right you are
committed in a gothic love to the child
children are resilient and they like
that doesn't mean you can be abusive or
neglected no but we tend to and this is
whether you're super uses statistics
agreed okay intervene we tend to magnify
the mistakes and it's oh no all right so
here's where trust in
your biological heritage your relational
resources and the deep you know
resiliency of children when they are
situated within an exotic context you
can have trust in that working on your
MBA I I hope you're doing all the
pedagogical and the interventions that
are strongly recommended I'm a teacher
you know you should get into a study
group you should be meeting with people
doing regular Q&A I know your time is
limited but tapping into distributed
cognition is one of the most powerful
ways to bootstrap your cognitive
flexibility your ability to learn and
your ability to reflect on material
dealing with your family business and
coded their I'm ignorant I'm sorry I
don't I'm not an entrepreneur I don't
have much knowledge about that I think
you're the question that follows up on
that about shifting into trying you know
not trying to always look for certainty
but to instead concentrate on building
adaptivity increasing your cognitive
flexibility increasing your meta
perspective all ability increasing the
the your connection right to all the
four kinds of knowing etc lots of things
that got lots of material out there the
lecture ISM the meditation contemplation
classes of how to enhance your
adaptivity stoicism are offers a really
wonderful place for really building up
adaptivity so those are things you can
do so try to keep the problems separate
and because there are different
strategies for the different problems
and I hope that was helpful for you it
won't always be the way it is now and I
know that's a stupid least simplistic
proposition but if you start to do some
of the things that's I'm recommending
what you want to do is can you start to
get a taste of the future you won't be
nourishing because
nothing's that up sleep in but if you
can start to get a taste of the future
that that acts as a powerful reminder
not just in thought but in the thoughts
of your being that it won't always be
this way and you won't always be this
way
don't give in to reciprocal narrowing I
encourage you there and encourage you
encourage you to keep going okay we're
going to shift to questions live
questions from the chat I want to thank
the patreon subscribers and everyone
watching right now your support is
crucial to continue to produce these
videos and for supporting the science
that we're doing to find solutions to
the media crisis and as you can know
they're telling reading that because
Omar has phrased it beautifully and I
wanted to get that right so here's a
question from MS o Van Wyck she is
regular attended to the the Sangha the
meditation livestream Thank You gizelle
for coming you have to mention the
dangers of a fragmented autodidactic
approach to wisdom in the meeting series
yes I do
I'm also quite aware that the dangers of
community approach yes Luke think etc
being indoctrinated isn't hid I was - as
well please say more so this goes
towards that sort of meta point and it's
one I like to return to again and again
because it's one that our culture keeps
forgetting there are so here's where
Tillich is very helpful to me we are
always pulled between individuation and
participation and there and when if the
individual Asian pole is too strong we
can become autodidactic and then we fall
prey to bias and self-deception but if
the participation pole is too strong we
can fall prey to cult-like behavior
groupthink and diffusion of
responsibility and all kinds of things
like Brazil I grew up in such a
situation and I found it quite hurtful
and to some degree traumatized it to me
and so the answer is that you we need to
create and this is telling sensors on my
answer we need to create persons within
a community with it we need to create
persons within a community that is
committed to the creation of persons
which means that we what should be
foremost in any community we want to
belong to is a recognition of these two
polar dangers that we want people to
have ongoing and richly rewarding access
to distributed cognition but we also
want people to be able to to hold it
they when they need to individuate pull
apart and offer critical reflection upon
group dynamics and we want individuals
who have been brought up to respect what
the community has to say but also
because the community has been committed
to a process of self correction be
encouraged to participate in the self
correction machinery other community
this was supposed to be and when you
redo it I mean that we could do what
Duty is are you John Dewey the American
private is philosopher and educate an
educational thinker I mean this is what
the but you know Julie saw that these
two things were supposed to always be
together there's these two great
self-correcting systems we have science
is a self-correcting system and
democracy and the idea is and the reason
why they tend to know well together is
to both self-correcting systems and when
people are in them they are
self-correcting systems of distributed
cognition that nevertheless in
individuals to try and make a critical
difference and that encourage
individuals to be different from those
around them and so in democracy we try
to balance the power of the majority off
against constitutional rights of the
individual and that's how and in
scientific practice we you know we you
have peer review and all this thing all
these things but the individual
scientists and the individual lab can is
basically doing their own thing and so
where there's that constant and then
these two things were supposed to
self-correct on each other so science
science was most do not be commodified
right and become largely driven by you
know funding and sort of publication
motives that are external to the quest
for knowledge and was supposed to be
held in check by sort of democracy
constantly remind reminding science of
its commitment to the community at large
and then if democracy was supposed to be
responsive to the way which science gave
us facts and information and whether or
not that's the case right now of course
is highly questionable but it is
possible that there happen it is
possible that given what Dewey has
argued that we can get a dynamical
system of opponent processing that
optimizes the relationship between
individuation of participation so that
we can constantly steer between and
that's what every virtue does it steers
you between you know particular vices of
excess or deficit we can get a virtue a
virtual engine that steers us between
other didacticism and group thing so
that's something that's very much on my
mind and the mind of people I'm working
with I know in this in trying to do this
project of community building Pete n
what role does temporality play in the
reciprocal narrowing and agogic paradigm
the Attic seems to lack vision or even
though
of the future yes I think that's
directly right Pete I think that when
when you get down to the reciprocal
narrowing and the world can't be any
other other than it is and I can't be
any other than I am and so this is a
Haida garyun argument I'm making right
once possibility is removed from being
something that is a phenomenological
presence then what's possibility in need
and possibility in the world and the
conjoined possibility is removed as a
present we lacked we lose we lose time
in the sense of that which is and this
is how there's idea that which is a mesh
with the unfolding of intelligibility
and being for us and so the future goes
away and and that's why there is no
sacred sec itself for the audit because
there is no viable future this is a
clear example of what I appointed to
before about where we can be in a place
where we could propositional II and with
images represent things the attact of
course has terms and propositions that
can refer to the future and he can
imagine or she can imagine future States
but that's not an existential future
it's not a viable future that they can
make a real developmental option for
them and so in that sense they are
trapped outside outside of time not an
eternity other it's a kind of help and
this is where not Gnostic mythology
often comes in a book being trapped in
this unreal kind of world like the no
time of the matrix within the movie of
the same name so mark the verb is here
I've got to meet mark face to face what
he's virtually wonderful person he does
so much so much wonderful support for
the meditation livestream community so
much on the discord server so much
excellent
you know education of others community
building
I mean this long theistic lead but I
mean it deeply mark as a godsend
so can you expand on their definition of
religion I like the short form
connectedness but I wonder if you had a
more comprehensive list feel for this
concept yes I do
what I mean by religio is the the
network of affordances that result from
the mutual sake shaping between all
three levels biological cultural and
cognitive level between the organism in
the environment that are being
constantly generated in a multi-layered
and dynamically recursive fashion by our
relevance realization machinery and
insofar as that is something that comes
into our awareness through all the
phenomenological normativity of each one
of the kinds of knowing the religio
comes into our sense of connectedness at
the participatory level when we have
that sense of belonging entombment it
comes into the perspectival level when
we have that sense of presence it comes
into the procedural level when we have
that sense of power and it comes into
the propositional level when we have
that sense of a conviction of truth and
it comes in what you might call a
ontological level when they are all
mutually stacked and we get the profound
understanding that grasps the
relationship of significance and dynamic
coupling between the kinds of knowing so
that's what I mean so religio right
that's why you can you you can sort of
lose religio at the participatory level
with culture shock or loneliness you can
lose it at the perspectival level when
you're with somebody that you know that
person is just not present or you
realize you're not being present with
them you can obviously get it at the
procedural level where your skills are
just weave you know with they're just
not working and it's just you feel
clumsy and out of sync and you can get
it on the propositional level when you
get the
that oh crap all of that was false
well that was false but you can also
have the opposite and more than just
those individually you can have all of
them mutually interpenetrating so that
you have deep connectedness that is
deeply understood and then that is when
we most have a phenomenological
appreciation all senses of the word
appreciation of religion Kevin R
Connelly assuming a I could one day
exhaust all possible pass and a
combinatorial explosion problem space
and find truly novel solutions is it
theoretically possible to make obscure
solutions salient for us so this it so I
don't know if I could do that what some
people think might be able to do that is
something like quantum computation but
I've now seen some arguments that look
like they're almost a priori arguments
then even quantum computation can't
cover accommodate or these are many
kinds of combinatorial explosive spaces
so whether or not it's possible is
really an open question I I don't think
classical machines will ever get to that
possibility and I think it's not
questionable of quantum mechanics that
machines will but what we could say in
answer to question is they certainly
could maybe explore the space get to a
place where they explore the space much
better I predict this will be some
hybrid kind of machine combining
classical computation with neural
networks and dynamical systems maybe
with a little bit of quantum stuff
thrown in because that's what we do we
are using some quantum stuff apparently
in our sense of smell and other things
why there who knows but let's say it's
plausible that we get machines that
could go much further could they find
things that are obscured to us
I think that's plausible because some of
these
more advanced machines especially ones
that are much more dynamically
self-organizing especially the ones that
have sort of these hybrid features like
our cognition again that's when we might
not be a collect it might be the you
need these hybrid type of machinery to
be generally intelligent but those
machines are already trying to already
finding things obscure solutions you
know ways of winning video games that no
human beings at the part of and also
things that are oh they're uncanny
they're creepy so I've seen my friend
Todd shared this with me a design for a
kind of its kind of like between a bolt
and a nut you know for for attaching
things that sort of optimally designed
to deal with stress and it's like no
human being would design this thing but
perhaps it is actually the best kind of
bolt we could come up with for attaching
things and it's really alien to creepy
so this reminds me of picket fence
things even of lions could talk we might
not understand that we might be just
orthogonal to these AI when they come
online let's hope not let's hope let's
hope that we could talk to them better
than we can talk to Lions that's a weird
thing to have said anyways is it
plausible that I think it's already
happening so I find that very plausible
that it's going to increase to increase
happening so I hope that answers your
question
so we're at the end it always seems like
it's goes by so fast I typically get
into something like a flow State doing
this and so I thank you all for that
I want to thank you for joining me in
this QA we do this every third Friday of
the month thank you for the supporters
at patreon you can support my work on
the meeting crisis at patreon.com slash
Toronto Vicky Woodward we have a discord
where people are having some really
interesting conversations of building
community testing other colleges of
practices linking
to the saying of the meditation
contemplation sign just wonderful
community having people there and there
are on voices with rebecky it's really
excellent true please check the
description in the link we are doing
that sit every weekday morning at 9:30
Eastern Time next Wednesday there won't
be a sip because of scheduling
difficulties I want to thank my dear
friend the techno major Maru is behind
the scenes as always making the magic
happening and keeping all patrols and
other mythological beasts at bay and I
hope to see you all next month thank you
very much one and all take care everyone